是, 大臣  第3季第4集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:英吉沙 校对&时间轴:tpring
操守问题
我们真的不会被指控浪费公款吧?
We can't be accused of wasting money?
当然不会 大臣      代表团已经缩到最小了?
Absolutely. We are taking the smallest delegation?
当然了 简直削皮见骨     那些人是谁?
Absolutely. Pared to the bone. Who are all those people?
我们的小代表团      你说削皮见骨的
Our delegation. You said it抎 been pared to the bone.
是的     那他们?
So it has. Who are they?
首先是外交部的小代表团
A small delegation from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.
可这是行政部的任务     是啊 可确实要出国
But this is a DAA mission. Yes, well, we are gong abroad.
外交问题 事关重大
Foreign policy is at stake.
我们将要签署有史以来
We're gong to ratify a contract
英国与波斯湾最大的出口协议
for one of the biggest export orders Britain抯 ever obtained.
但这是英国电子设备公司谈成的
That was negotiated by British Electronic Systems.
那些公务员来干什么?
Who are all these civil servants?
外贸部有个代表团 工业部也有
There's a delegation from Trade and one from industry.
能源部有个小组 毕竟我们要去石油国家
There's a group from Energy. We are gong to an oil sheikdom.
常务副长带领的内阁办公室的团
There's a Deputy Secretary leading a team from the Cabinet Office.
还有情报部的团
There's a group from the Central Office of Information,
还有我们行政部的团
and there's our DAA team.
新闻秘书 私人秘书 联络秘书
Press secretaries, private secretaries, liaison secretaries.
法律部 草拟合同的 监督合同的
The legal department who did the contract supervised it.
削皮见骨?     削皮见骨
Pared to the bone? To the bone.
可我们在米德郡见面的时候 只带了7个人
If we'd met in Middlesbrough, we'd have only taken seven people.
没错 可米德郡的外交意义恐怕不如库朗
Teesside is not quite so diplomatically significant as kumran.
米德郡有4位议员      库朗控制壳牌和英国石油
Teesside returns four MPs. Kumran controls Shell and BP.
你来干什么?     完全出于"免税"考虑
What are you doling here? Purely my sense of duty-free.
免税?
Duty-free?
免除私人考虑 纯为纳税人着想
Er... duty, free from any personal consideration.
请您先看看这个     是什么?
Look through this. What is it?
是最终公报     最终公报?
it抯 the final communiqu? The final?
怎能在会前就写公报?
You can't write it before the meeting!
正相反 大臣 不能留到会后写公报
On the contrary, you can't write it after the meeting.
我们得跟诸多部门达成共识
We had to get agreement from other departments,
欧共体 华盛顿 库朗大使馆
the EEC, Washington, the kumrani Embassy.
在一片沙漠里根本忙不过来
You can't do that in the desert.
这跟我们要讲的完全没关系
It may bear no relation to what we say.
公报跟我们要讲的一向没关系
No communiqu?ever bears any relation to what you say.
那为什么要写?     好让媒体有东西报道
Then why have one? It gets you past the press corps.
记者需要解释他们采访这件无用功的昂贵账单
journalists justly their expenses for a futile non-event.
无用功?     哦 您会功勋显赫的 大臣
Non-event? A brilliant triumph for you, Minister.
所以对媒体来说就是无用功了
Which is why it抯 a futile non-event for the press.
他们巴不得我在招待会上撒酒疯
They'd like me to get drunk at the reception.
是啊 但这次没指望了 库朗很枯燥
Yes. Not much hope of that. Kumran is dry.
对 那当然 沙漠中央嘛
Yeah. Well, of course, It is in the middle of the desert.
你是说 伊斯兰教法?     唉 是的
You mean... Islamic law Alas, yes.
英国大使馆有酒的吧     是的
We can get a drink at the British Embassy?
使馆有 可招待会和晚宴在皇宫举行
Yes. But the reception and the dinner are at the palace.
五小时的橘子汁
Five hours of orange juice.
五个小时 滴酒不沾?
Five hours? Without a single drinky
你怎能让我出这种差 汉弗莱?
Why did you let me come on this trip?
怎么办 裤兜里藏酒壶?
What are we gong to do? Hip flasks?
不行 太冒险了 只好咬牙强忍
No, much too risky. We have to grin and bear it.
能不能设一个秘密通讯室?
Why don抰 we set up a security communications room
就在宴会厅隔壁?
next door to the reception?
紧急电话 直通唐宁街的电报线之类
You know, emergency telephones, telex lines to Downing Street.
把使馆带去的酒藏在里面
Then we could fill it with booze brought in from the Embassy.
大臣     给橘汁加点料
Minister! Liven up the orange juice!
这简直是...天才的主意
That is a... stroke of genius!
能做到吗?     重大危机才需要秘密通讯室
Could it be done? Such a room would need a major crisis.
五小时橘汁就是重大危机
Five hours on orange juice Is a major crisis.
英镑走势确实不好      能安排吗?
The pound is under pressure. Could you arrange it?
大臣 您的指示 我保证强力支持
your instructions I can guarantee my support.
您真是太慷慨了
Most awfully generous of you
这礼物真是美极了
to present me with this very splendid gift.
很荣幸能给您留下美好回忆
It is a great pleasure to commemorate this day.
太美了
It's so beautiful!
17世纪伊斯兰艺术的典型代表
A magnificent example of 17th-century Islamic art.
原本是做什么用的?     玫瑰香水罐
What was it originally? A rosewater jar.
明白了 是...放玫瑰香水的?     正是
I see. For rosewater, presumably? Quite so.
打扰了 大臣 通讯室有紧急电话 是海格先生
Mr Haig call you in communications room
海格将军吗?
General Haig?
不 海格先生 有"酒窝"那位(海格添宝威士忌)
No, Mr. Haig. You know, with the dlmples.
好好 失礼了 这很重要
Yes, yes. Do excuse me. Most important.
据说海格先生找我     是的 大臣
I believe there's a message from Mr Haig. Yes, Minister.
我是这唯一的女人     是的 这是特许
I'm the only woman here. Special dispensation.
今晚他们把您奉为男人
They've made you an honorary man for the evening.
放我家门厅一定很漂亮     哈克夫人 我不确定
This will look wonderful on our hall table.
什么?     这是给大臣的礼物
If what? it抯 a gift to the minister.
也是他家门厅
It's his hall, too.
不 恐怕您不能留着它     为什么?
I don't think you'll be allowed to keep it. Why ever not?
如果它很值钱 会对某些大臣有影响
if it were valuable, It could influence some ministers.
不是您的大臣 是我的大臣
Not your minister, that is, my minister
我们大臣 就是您丈夫
our minister. Your husband, as it were.
就是这样 我是说...有些大臣...
As it is, in fact. I mean, he is. I mean... Well, some ministers...
伯纳     抱歉
Bernard. Sorry.
你是说把它还回去?     不 那会被当作侮辱
Are you saying we have to give it back? No, that'd be an insult.
不能留 不能还 那怎么办?      会变成政府财产
We can't give it back. It becomes government property.
放在白厅地下室里     真的不能留吗?
it抯 put in a basement in Whitehall. You sure we can't keep it?
除非价值低于50镑     怎么确定呢?
Not if it抯 worth more than 50. How do we find out?
通过估价     你能找人估价吗
You get a valuation. Could you get a valuation?
如果它不值50镑多好 真是太漂亮了
Wouldn't it be wonderful if it was less than 50?
那个 我...
Well, I...
我想我能试试     哦 伯纳 你真好
I suppose I could try. Oh, Bernard, you are wonderful!
我们真不能没有你啊
What would we do without you?
啊 伯纳 通讯室在找你
Bernard. Wanted in the communications room.
尊尼获加先生
A Mr John Walker.
尊尼获加?      对 威士忌事务部...抱歉
Johnnie Walker? Yes, from the Scotch Office... Sorry.
苏格兰事务部     有没有找我的电话?
Scottish Office. Isn't there a message for me?
当然有
Yes, of course.
让伯纳转给你 如果你给他个杯子...我是说
Bernard will get it for you if you give him your glass. If you...
给他个杯子 他再给你倒杯橘汁
give him your glass, he'll get you some more orange juice.
伯纳 汉弗莱在这儿吗?     对 在那边
Is Humphrey here yet? Yes, he's just over here.
失陪
Excuse me.
借过
大臣     这究竟...?
Minister. What on earth?
外交部对阿拉伯朋友的友好传统 不是吗
Traditional Foreign Office courtesy to our Arab hosts
一点没错 小汉 对吗 殿下
Spot on, Humpy. Isn't that right, Your Royal Highness?
对 我们认为这是一种慷慨赞誉
Yes, we regard it as a warm and gracious compliment.
这位是大臣 这位是穆罕默德王子
May I present our minister? This is Prince Mohammed.
您好 王子     不胜荣幸 阁下
How do you do? Pleased to meet you, Your Excellency.
"阁下"啊 如果您允许
Excellency! I say, if you'll excuse me,
我要和汉弗莱爵士说几句话
I just must have a quick word with Sir Humphrey.
我简直不敢相信 你以为你是谁 阿里巴巴?
I can't believe my eyes! What are you here as? All Baba?
大臣 入乡随俗嘛     你也太"俗"了 真滑稽
Minister, when in Rome... We are not in Rome. You look ridiculous!
要是在斐济岛 你要穿草裙不成?
If we were in the Fiji Islands, you'd wear a grass skirt!
外交部认为 阿拉伯人非常敏感
The Foreign Office view, as Arabs are sensitive,
该由我们表明自己站哪边
Is we should show them whose side we're on.
外交部可能会觉得奇怪
It may come as a surprise to them
但你应该站我们这边
but you're supposed to be on our side!
伯纳 有电话吗?     有一通给汉弗莱爵士的
Bernard, any messages? Well, there is one for Sir Humphrey.
哦 很好
Oh, good.
苏联使馆的宝狮将军(伏特加)
The Soviet Embassy on the line. Mr Smirnoff.
失陪了 抱歉
Sorry. So sorry.
有我的么?
Isn't there one for me?
大使馆来电话 学校的 教师代表团(狄澈威士忌)
There was a message from a delegation of Teachers.
啊 得去问候一下教师们...
Ah, I must go and greet the Teachers...
在上课铃(啤酒)响之前
before the Bells goes... bell goes!
你们的紧急电话很多啊
You're receiving a great many very urgent messages.
对对 确实是     噢 伯纳 失礼
Yes, yes, we are, aren抰 we? Excuse me.
殿下 我来介绍一下培宁顿先生
Your Royal Highness, could I present Mr Pennington?
失陪了     没关系 殿下
Excuse me. Yes, of course, Your Highness.
抱歉 但我无意中听到
Excuse me, but I could not help overhearing
你们要给一件礼物估价
your conversation about valuing the gift.
或许我能帮个小忙     这就太...
Perhaps I can help. That would be...
您知道值多少钱吗?     当然
Do you have any idea how much? Of course.
真的17世纪的玫瑰香水罐很昂贵的
An original 17th-century rosewater jar Is very valuable.
哦 天哪     您不高兴吗?
Oh, dear. You are not pleased?
是也不是 如果很值钱 大臣就不能留下了
Yes and no. If it抯 valuable, the minister won't be allowed to keep it.
我希望它不那么值钱
I was rather hoping it wasn抰.
我刚说
As I was saying,
17世纪的玫瑰香水罐 真品很昂贵
an original 17th-century rosewater jar is very valuable,
但这件仿制品 尽管逼真 却大不相同
but this copy, though excellently done, Is not of the same order.
太好了 大概多少钱?
Oh, good. About how much?
我想让你来猜猜看
I would be interested to hear your guess.
差不多...低于50镑?
Er... well, a little under... 50?
太厉害了 您真是位内行
Brilliant! Quite a connoisseur!
您能签估价证明吗?
And you would sign a valuation certificate?
当然了
But of course.
你们英国人真奇怪     怎么?
Your English customs are very strange. Oh, why?
你们对一件小礼物如此严苛
You are so strict about a gift,
可你们电子公司又给我们金融部长几百万美元
your company pays our finance minister a million dollars
保证合同的签署
to secure this contract.
这不奇怪吗?
Is this not strange?
你 你难道是说      当然
You... You don't mean... Of course.
我就是为金融部长工作的 我也有份
I work for the minister. I got my share.
用来干什么?     遮口费啊
What for? For keeping my mouth shut.
我明白了 抱歉我先走了
II see. Would you excuse me For a moment?
大臣 我能跟汉弗莱爵士私下说句话吗?
Minister, can I have a private word with Sir Humphrey?
你尽管说吧小伯纳
You may speak freely, Bernie.
好的...哦 通讯室有您的电话
There was a message for you in the room.
提税的 来提您的69号     什么?
The VAT man, your 69 returns. What?
提纯69号(威士忌)
VAT69.
好好 谢谢你
Yes... thanks.
我突然发现 伯纳
I'm rapidly coming to the conclusion
大臣接的紧急电话
that the minister has had
已经到达极限了
almost as many urgent messages as he can take.
我发现了更可怕的事     天哪
I've found out the most terrible thing. Dear me.
那份合同是贿赂来的
This contract was obtained by bribery.
当然
Of course.
库朗每份合同都是贿赂来的
All contracts in kumran are obtained by bribery.
人人都知道
Everybody knows that.
没关系 只要没人知道就行
It's all right, as long as nobody knows.
不该告诉大臣吗?     当然不该
Shouldn抰 we tell the minister? Certainly not.
但人人都知道     除了大臣
But if everybody knows. Everybody else.
不能让大臣知道人人都知道的事
We do not let a minister know what everybody else knows.
殿下 幸会幸会
Highness, how very nice to see you.
阿拉伯的劳伦斯 通讯室找你呢
you're wanted in the communications room.
好的 是谁?
Oh, good. Er, who is it?
拿破仑(白兰地)
Napoleon!
"世界报声称 英国最近与库朗的合同"
"Le Monde says the British contract with kumran
"是贿赂来的"
was won by bribery."
你听见了吗 汉弗莱?     是的 大臣
Do you hear this, Humphrey? Yes, indeed.
"这张骇人听闻的腐败之网"
"It's part of a hideous web of corruption
"由西方工业国家与第三世界"
woven by Western Industrial countries
"合织而成"
and Third World governments
"是我们现代文明的一个污点"
that forms a blot of our modern civilisation."
网不会变成污点 大臣      什么?
Webs don't form blots, Minister. What?
蜘蛛没有墨水 您看
Well, spiders don't have any ink, you see.
只有墨鱼才有
Only cuttlefish.
蜘蛛没有…你在说什么?     我知道
What are you talking about? I know...
谢谢 伯纳     太可怕了吧 空穴来风
Thank you, Bernard. Isn't this terrible? Baseless accusations!
是是 真可怕
Oh, yes, yes, terrible.
好处费 回扣 天啊 我们可是英国人
Backsheesh, palm-greasing! Good God, we're British!
毋庸置疑 大臣
Absolutely, Minister!
金融时报不太可能空穴来风
It's not like the FT to print a story like this
除非幕后另有文章
unless there's something behind it.
幕后有文章吗 汉弗莱?
Is there something behind it, Humphrey?
我想后面是体育新闻
I think the sports news Is behind it.
我想知道真相 汉弗莱     您不想 大臣
I want to know the truth, Humphrey. I don't think you do.
你能直接回答吗?     我强烈建议您不要直接问
Will you answer a direct question?
为什么?     因为我可能直接回答
Why? It might provoke a direct answer.
你从没直接过
It never has yet.
伯纳 你知道怎么回事吗? 老实告诉我
What do you know about this? Tell me!
那个 我...是这样的 有人
Oh, well, I... Er, that is... there was. Someone did.
传言而已 大臣 传闻 道听途说
A lot of gossip, that's all. Rumour, hearsay.
伯纳?
Bernard?
有个库朗人说他收到了...     道听途说 大臣
One kumrani did tell me he'd received... Hearsay, Minister.
道听途说?     伯纳半道听到了他说
Hearsay? Yes, Bernard heard him say it.
汉弗莱 你是说合同确实是贿赂来的?
Are you telling me that the contract was won by bribery
大臣 请您别用贿赂这个词
I do wish you wouldn't use words like bribery.
那要用什么词? 脏钱 甜头 红包?
What would you like me to say? Slush funds, brown envelopes?
大臣 这词太残酷无理了
These are extremely crude and unworthy expressions
不能形容这种创意谈判
for what is no more than creative negotiation.
这是潜规则罢了
It is general practice.
你知道你在说什么吗? 我签合同是出于良心
You do realise what you're saying?
是 大臣      公报里我说
In that press communiqu?
英国是通过公平竞争赢的
I announced a British success won in a fair fight!
是的 这部分我也好奇来着
Yes, I did wonder about that bit.
现在你说 是贿赂来的     不 大臣
Now you're telling me It was got by bribery.
哦 不是贿赂来的      我没这么说
Oh, it was not got by bribery That is not what I said.
你怎么说?
What did you say?
我说我没告诉您那是贿赂来的
That I'm not telling you It was got by bribery.
你怎么形容合同的支付款项?
How would you describe these payments?
合同是怎么形容的?      对
How does the contract describe them?
哦 这就简单了
Oh, well, that's quite simple.
聘金 私人捐献 特别折扣
Retainers, personal donations, special discounts.
杂项开支 中介费
Miscellaneous outgoings, agents' fees,
政治献金 管理支出
political contributions, management expenses.
这些款项是怎么支付的?
How are these payments made?
各种渠道 从瑞士银行帐号
Anything from a numbered Swiss account
到洗手间门缝的小信封都有
to a fistful of used oncers slipped under the door of the gents'.
你知道这有多可怕吗?      地域偏见罢了
Do you realise how shocking this is? That is a narrow view.
世上另一些地区 人们持有不同的意见
In other parts of the world, they see things differently.
罪恶不分地域 汉弗莱     但确实有关
Sin is not a branch of geography. But it is.
在发展中国家 合同外支付金的数额
In developing countries, the size of the extra contractual payment
代表我们的诚意
shows how serious you are.
就像出版社提前的支付作家版税
It's like a publisher抯 advance to an author.
谁出的高 代表谁的预期销售额高
Whoever pays the biggest advance expects the biggest sales.
我简直不敢相信
I don't believe it!
难道腐败也是政府的政策?
Is corruption government policy?
不 大臣 腐败从来就不是政策
No, no, Minister! It could never be government policy!
简直不可思议 它只是政府惯例
That is unthinkable! Only government practice.
新闻办打来的 大臣
That was the press office.
报纸希望您对贿赂事件发表声明
The papers want a statement about the bribery allegation.
声明 我能说什么呢?
What am I gong to say?
新闻办总有一套有说服力的空话
The press office can devise something convincing
这是他们的工作
That's what they're paid for.
你是个愤世者 汉弗莱     愤世者
You're a cynic, Humphrey. Cynic.
愤世者是理想主义者对现实主义者的称呼
A cynic is what an idealist calls a realist.
我必须说出事实 我毕竟对此一无所知
I'll tell the truth. After all, I knew nothing of this.
不是我安排的 凭什么要我负责?
Why should I back something I never approved?
可这合同里有几千份英国工人的工作
But this contract means thousands of British jobs,
上百万出口额
millions of export dollars!
您不会为一点操作不规范就抛弃它们吧?
you won't throw that away because technical irregularly?
这不是"操作不规范" 这是腐败
It's not a technical irregularly, It is corruption!
不 大臣 只是合同外的预付金
No. Merely a few subcontracted pre-payments.
汉弗莱 我不指望你理解
I don't expect you to understand,
但政府执政不光是手腕和心眼
but government is not just a question of fixing and manipulating.
还有操守问题      可不是 操守问题
There is a moral dimension. of course, the moral dimension.
我从没忘记过这个问题
It is never out of my thoughts.
如果媒体问我 我将宣布展开调查
So if questions are asked in the press, I shall announce an inquiry.
好主意 大臣 我很乐意主持
Splendid idea. I shall be happy to conduct it.
不 不 不
No, no, no, no, no.
不是内部调查 是真的调查
No, not an internal inquiry, a real inquiry.
大臣 您开玩笑吧     一场真的调查
You can't be serious! A real inquiry.
大臣 求您了     汉弗莱 操守问题
I beg you... Humphrey... the moral dimension.
晚上好 哈克夫人     伯纳 请进
Good evening, Mrs Hacker. Bernard, come in.
谢谢     是你吗 伯纳?
Thank you. Is that you, Bernard?
是我 大臣     我马上来
Yes, Minister. Shan't be a moment.
是库朗的香水罐
There's that jar from kumran.
是啊 我有个朋友非常感兴趣
A friend of mine was frightfully interested in it.
是吗?     珍妮古德温 卫报的
Really? Jenny Goodwin from The Guardian.
卫报?     她问哪来的
The Guardian? She asked where it came from.
她是个记者?     是啊 虽然是卫报
A journalist? Yes. Well, The Guardian, anyway.
她问值多少钱 我说50镑      你说50镑
She asked what it was worth. I said 50. You said 50.
对 奇怪的是 她认为这是真品
Funnlly enough, she thought it was genulne.
她认为这是真品
She thought It was genulne?
对 伯纳 你听起来像部电话答录机
Bernard, you sound like an answerlng machlne.
噢 抱歉
Oh, I'm sorry.
她要打电话问库朗大使馆 它到底值多少
She wanted to rlng kumran's Embassy to ask what it was worth.
问它到底值多少
To ask what it was worth.
您怎么说?     我说 随便你
So what did you say? I said, by all means.
这确实是仿的 不是吗?
It is only a copy, isn抰 it?
那个...据我所知...
Well... so far as I'm...
我也...天哪 几点了?
so I'm lead to... Good gracious, is that the time?
伯纳     抱歉 大臣要晚几分钟到
Sorry, the minister will be a few minutes late.
我过会儿再来
I'll come back.
其实 汉弗莱爵士 我想跟您说句话
Actually, I wonder if I could have a word.
好
Yes.
我说好     是 我知道
I said yes. Yes, I know.
您瞧
You see...
出岔子了 伯纳?
Something the matter, Bernard?
开口吧 说出来
Come on, out with it.
你送大臣去错了晚宴?
Did you send the minister to the wrong dinner?
拿错了他的演讲稿?
Give him the wrong speech?
给他看了我们不想让他看的文件?
Show him some papers we didn抰 mean him to see?
更糟?
Worse?
还要更糟?
Much worse?
坐下
Sit down.
好吧 全告诉我
Well... tell me about it.
您知道大臣在库朗收的香水罐吧
You know that jar the minister was given in kumran?
大臣夫人...非常中意
Well, the minister's wife... liked it.
我想也是
I expect she did.
我跟她解释了规定 她好像...很伤心
Then, when I explained the rules to her, she looked... terribly sad.
他们都这样
They always do.
她说要是不值50英镑该有多好
She said wouldn't it be marvellous if it wasn't worth more than 50
她还...瞅着我
and she sort of... looked at me.
可我的好伯纳 一个17世纪的水罐
But, my dear Bernard, a 17th-century vase!
我知道 但正好有个非常和善的库朗商人
Yes, I know, but there was this terribly nice kumrani businessman
我们就...谈了一会儿
and we had a... a... a... conversation
他鉴定那罐子是仿制品 49.95镑
and he valued it as a copy, not as an original -49.95p.
你就信了     他说他是专家
You believed him. He said he was an expert.
他阿拉伯语说得非常棒
He spoke Arabic awfully well...
所以我就相信他的诚实了
and so I accepted his valuation in good faith.
毕竟 伊斯兰教很诚实的
After all, Islam is a jolly good faith.
伯纳 你太冒险了
You took a grave personal risk.
算你走运 还没人问
You're lucky nobody's asked questions.
对 可是卫报有个记者在大臣家看见了
A journalist saw it in the minister's house
提了很多疑问
and asked a lot of questions.
哈克夫人说那是仿的 可媒体...
Mrs Hacker said it was a copy, but the press are so...
他们都非常多疑
horribly suspicious about things.
真卑鄙     那我该怎么办呢
Despicable! So... what shall I do?
必须告诉大臣
The minister must be told.
抱歉让你久等了
Sorry to keep you.
没关系 您读了我的建议吗 大臣?
That's all right. Have you read my submission?
是的 但那不可行
I did, and it won抰 do.
我不会让人指控我包庇贿赂
I won't be accused of sweeping bribery under the carpet.
媒体问起 我会宣布由皇室律师主持调查
I will announce an inquiry chaired by a QC.
大臣 您不能 那合同值34000万
You can't! That contract is worth 340 million!
我不在乎 汉弗莱 操守问题
Get thee behind me, Humphrey! The moral dimension.
大臣 真要展开调查 其他事也会泄露
Minister, if there is an inquiry, other things may come out, too.
什么事?
Such as?
恐怕伯纳有话想说
I'm afraid Bernard... has something to tell you.
嗯?
Well?
您记得库朗送您那个水罐吧
You know that jar the kumranis gave you?
对 在我家摆着 非常漂亮
Yes, it抯 at the flat now. Most attractive.
我告诉哈克夫人 价值低于50镑才能留着
I told Mrs Hacker she could keep it if its less than 50.
估价人非常和蔼 我告诉他哈克太太很喜欢
The value was awfully nice and I told him Mrs Hacker liked it a lot,
于是他就...帮了点忙
but he may have been just, well, being helpful.
没关系 伯纳
It's all right, Bernard.
没人会知道的 你真会打算盘
No one will ever know. Jolly enterprising of you.
哈克夫人说有个记者问过她
Mrs Hacker told me a journalist was asking questions.
记者?     我能看看估价报告吗?
Journalist? Can I just see that valuation?
嗯 财政部不会喜欢
The Treasury isn抰 too happy
写在菜单背面的估价报告的
about valuations written on the backs of menus.
这份菜单很不错的
It is a very good menu.
到底值多少?
What is it worth?
如果是仿的 就值估的价钱
If it抯 a copy, what the valuation says.
如果是...原件呢?
And if it抯... genulne?
差不多5000镑
About 5,000.
天啊 我居然就拿了
Oh, my God, I kept it!
大臣 新闻办的比尔找您
Bill from the press office wants to talk to you.
不 伯纳 我正忙着你这码事呢
I'm trying to deal with this problem you've landed me with!
他就是说这个
That's what he wants to talk to you about.
什么?
Well?
大臣 外交部全乱套了
The Foreign and Commonwealth Office is in a frightful state.
哈克夫人告诉卫报说 库朗赠送的极度珍贵的
Mrs Hacker has told The Guardian that valuable 17th-century thing
17世纪艺术品是复制品
presented to you by kumran was a copy.
卫报打电话给库朗大使馆求证
The Guardian phoned the kumrani Embassy for their comments.
库朗非常愤怒 这暗示他们送给您假货
The kumran angry at the suggestion they insulted Britain
借以侮辱英国
by giving you a worthless gift.
这已成了"公主之死"以来最大的外交危机
It's the biggest diplomatic incident since "Death of a Princess".
有位卫报记者在外面等着见您
There's a reporter demanding to see you right away.
什么 伯纳?
Yes, Bernard?
大臣 您打算...     伯纳 我清楚我的责任
Minister... what are you... Bernard, my duty is clear.
我别无选择     别无选择?
I have no choice. No choice?
别无选择 伯纳 不是我让你骗我太太
No choice. I didn抰 ask you to lie to my wife
捏造礼物价格的
about the value of that gift.
不 但是...
No, but...
伯纳 我知道你是出于好意
I realise you acted from the purest motives.
但是抱歉 伪造文件的罪名无法推卸
But there can be no excuse for falsifying a document.
但我...     听我说完
But I... Let me continue.
我不能让人说 是我指使的你
I cannot have it said that I asked you to do this.
也不能被指责纵容腐败与贿赂
that I connived at bribery and corruption.
该适可而止了
Enough is enough.
如果记者直接提问
If this journalist asks me straight questions
关于这两件事
on either of these subjects...
我都会给她明确答复
I shall have to give her straight answers.
操守问题
The moral dimension.
大臣 我非常同意
Minister, I agree with you.
现在我明白了 什么事都要讲操守
I see now that there is a moral dimension to everything.
是您去告诉媒体那间紧急通讯室 还是我去?
Will you tell the press about the communications room or shall I?
什么?
What?
您知道的 在库朗喝的威士忌
You know, all the Scotch in kumran.
你是说 如果我说了...你就...
You mean to tell me that... If I say...
你就说...
then you will... tell...
陷我于...
and drop me in the...
陷您于操守问题
in the moral dimension.
这完全不一样
This is different!
根本就是两码事      怎么?
it抯 not the same thing! Why?
饮酒不是腐败     对 只是欺骗而已
Drinking, it抯 not corruption. No, it抯 just deceit.
欺骗?     我们欺骗了库朗人
Deceit? We have deceived the kumranis.
我良心极度不安
I'm racked with guilt.
饱受折磨 因为我们
Tormented by the knowledge
侵犯了神圣的伊斯兰教法 就在他们国土上
that we violated their sacred Islamic law in their own country.
迟早得站出来承认 那是您的主意
we'll have to own up and admit that it was your idea.
不是我     就是你
It wasn抰! It was!
不是我...是我吗?
It wasn抰... was it?
处50下鞭刑还是100下?
Is it 50 lashes or 100?
大臣 您必须见这个记者 不然她肯定胡编
I must ask you to meet this journalist.
是 好吧 可我能说什么呢?
Oh, yes, all right. What am I gong to say?
我建议 进攻是最好的防御
I suggest attack Is the best form of defence.
进攻 进攻 好主意 汉弗莱 明白了
Attack, attack, yes. Good thinking, Humphrey. Yes, got it.
大臣 卫报的珍妮古德温
Miss Jenny Goodwin from The Guardian.
请进 请坐 珍妮 可以叫你珍妮吗?
Do come in. Sit down, Jenny. I may call you Jenny, may I not?
随您便     好 有什么问题?
If you like. Now, what seems to be the trouble?
有两件事 大臣 公众都非常忧心
Two things. Both of them Rather worrying to the public.
第一件 您可能已经在法国"世界报"读到了
The first is a story that was in the French press.
电子公司靠贿赂与库朗签合同的事
It's about corruption in BES, getting the kumrani contract.
纯粹胡说八道
Complete nonsense!
可他们有官方付款报告
They quoted reports of payments to officials.
这简直太典型了
Really, this is absolutely typical.
一家英国公司呕心沥血争取订单 创造岗位
A British company slogs its guts out to win orders, create jobs!
媒体的评价呢? 完全是泼脏水
What does it get from the medal? A smear campaign!
但如果确实有贿赂...
If they won by bribery...
没有贿赂 我进行了全面调查
There was no bribery. I had a full inquiry.
所有付款都有正当名目
All these payments have been identified.
比如?
What as?
中介费 行政开支
Commission fees, administrative overheads.
运营成本 管理附加费
Operative costs, managerial surcharges.
特别款项 杂项开支
Expenses, miscellaneous outgoings.
我们检查了每个红包...
We have looked into every brown envelope...
每个...
every...
每个银行账户 全都非常合理
every account book and everything is completely in order.
我明白了     我能再说一件事吗?
I see. May I say one thing?
此事显示出了我们社会的病态
Allegations of this nature are symptomatic of a very sick society
媒体恐怕也有责任
for which the medal shares the blame!
媒体?
The medal?
你们怎能拿千万工作岗位冒险?
Why are you putting thousands of jobs at risk?
我会提请报业评议会进行审查
I'll call on the Press Council to censure the press
这次的报道毫无职业道德 骇人听闻
for its lack of professionalism in running this story.
评议会和下院必须重视
The Council and the House of Commons must be concerned
这起恶劣事件带来的深远影响
about the standards which have applied in this disgraceful matter.
政府必须施压 从而确保
Pressure will be brought to bear to make sure
这种垃圾报道不再出现
that this gutter press reporting Is not repeated.
明白了
I see.
嗯 还有一个问题
Well, there is this other question.
关于一只玫瑰香水罐
It's about the rosewater jar
库朗方面送您的
apparently presented to you in kumran.
怎么?     我在您家里看见了
Yes? I saw it in your flat, actually.
对 我们放在那了 临时的     临时的?
Yes, we're keeping it there, temporally. Temporally?
对 它太贵重了      哈克夫人说那是仿的
Yes, it抯 very valuable. Mrs Hacker said it was an imitation.
防贼啊 姑娘 防贼
Burglars, girl, burglars!
你还四处传闲话 反正很快就会处理掉
And you've gossip! That's until we can get rid of it.
处理掉?
Get rid of it?
这个周末我将把它赠给地方博物馆
I'll present it to our local museum this weekend.
我不能留下的 这是政府财产
I can't hold onto it, you know. It's government property.
好 你要问什么?
Now... what was your question?
不...实际上 没什么
No... er... that's all right, actually.
我...不 差不多了
Um... I... No, no, no, that's fine.
没问题了?     没有没有 就这些了
Nothing more? No, no, that's all.
很好 多谢你来访
Well, good of you to drop in.
谢谢您 大臣     再见 珍妮
Thank you, Minister. Goodbye, Jenny.
精彩绝伦 大臣
Superb, Minister.
谢谢 大臣     噢 这没什么
Thank you, Minister. Oh, well, it was nothing.
人要忠于朋友嘛 嗯 汉弗莱? 嗯 伯纳?
We must stick by one's friends, eh, Humphrey? Eh, Bernard?
忠诚
Loyalty.
是 大臣
Yes, Minister.